down. Chapter 12. Inside information.
For a long time the dwarves stood in the dark before the door and debated until
at last Doran spoke. Now is the time for our esteemed Mr. Baggins, who has proved
himself a good companion on our long road, and a hobbit full of courage and
resource far exceeding his size, and if I may say so, possessed of good luck,
far exceeding the usual allowance. Now is the time for him to perform the
service for which he was included in our company. Now is the time for him to earn
his reward.
You are familiar with Thoren style on important occasions, so I will not give
you any more of it, though he went on a good deal longer than this. It certainly
was an important occasion, but Bilbo felt impatient.
By now he was quite familiar with Thoren, too, and he knew what he was
driving at. If you mean you think it is my job to go into the secret passage
first. Oh Thorenthra son Oakenshield, may your beard grow ever longer, he said
crossly. Say so at once and have done. I might refuse. I have got you out of two
messes already, which were hardly in the original bargain, so that I am, I think,
already owed some reward. But third time pays for all, as my father used to say,
and somehow I don't think I shall refuse. Perhaps I have begun to trust my
luck more than I used to in the old days. He met last spring before he left
his own house, but it seems centuries ago. But anyway, I think I will go and
have a peep at once and get it over.
Now, who was coming with me? He did not expect a chorus of volunteers, so he was
not disappointed.
Feelely and Keely looked uncomfortable and stood on one leg, but the others
made no pretense of offering, except old Balin, the lookout man, who was rather
fond of the hobbit. He said he would come inside at least, and perhaps a bit
of the way, too, ready to call for help if necessary.
The most that can be said for the dwarves is this. They intended to pay
Bilbo really handsomely for his services. They had brought him to do a
nasty job for them, and they did not mind the poor little fellow doing it if
he would. But they would all have done their best to get him out of trouble if
he got into it, as they did in the case of the trolls at the beginning of their
adventures before they had any particular reasons for being grateful to
him. There it is. Dwarves are not heroes, but calculating folk with a
great idea of the value of money. Some are tricky and treacherous and pretty
bad lots. Some are not, but are decent enough people like Thoren and company if
you don't expect too much. The stars were coming up behind him in a pale sky
barred with black when the hobbit crept through the enchanted door and stole
into the mountain. It was far easier going than he expected. This was no
goblin entrance or roughwood elves cave.
It was a passage made by dwarves at the height of their wealth and skill,
straight as a ruler, smooth floored and smoothsided, going with a gentle, never
varying slope direct to some distant end in the blackness below.
After a while, Balene bade Bilbo good luck and stopped where he could still
see the faint outline of the door, and by a trick of the echoes of the tunnel,
hear the rustle of the whispering voices of the others just outside. Then the
hobbit slipped on his ring, and warned by the echoes to take more than hobbit's
care to make no sound, he crept nolessly down, down, down into the dark. He was
trembling with fear, but his little face was set and grim. Already he was a very
different hobbit from the one that had run out without a pocket handkerchief
from Bagen long ago. He had not had a pocket handkerchief for ages. He
loosened his dagger in its sheath, tightened his belt, and went on. "Now
you are in for it at last, Bilbo Baggins," he said to himself. You went
and put your foot right in it that night of the party, and now you have got to
pull it out and pay for it. Dear me,
what a fool I was in am, said the least turquish part of him. I have absolutely
no use for dragonarded treasures, and the whole lot could stay here forever.
If only I could wake up and find this beastly tunnel was my own front hull at
home. He did not wake up, of course, but
went still on and on to all sign of the door behind it faded away. He was
altogether alone.
Soon he thought it was beginning to feel warm. Is that a kind of a glow I seemed
to see coming right ahead down there? He thought it was. As he went forward, it
grew and grew till there was no doubt about it. It was a red light steadily
getting redder and redder. Also, it was now undoubtedly hot in the tunnel. Wisps
of vapor floated up and passed him, and he began to sweat. A sound, too, began
to thro in his ears, a sort of bubbling like the noise of a large pot galloping
on the fire, mixed with a rumble as of a gigantic tomat purring. This grew to the
unmistakable gurgling noise of some vast animal snoring in its sleep down there
in the red glow in front of him.
It was at this point that Bilbo stopped.
Going on from there was the bravest thing he ever did. The tremendous things
that happened afterwards were as nothing compared to it. He fought the real
battle in the tunnel alone, before he ever saw the vast danger that lay in
weight. At any rate, after a short halt, go on he did, and you can picture him
coming to the end of the tunnel, an opening of much the same size and shape
as the door above. Through it peeps the hobbit's little head. Before him lies
the great bottommost cellar or dungeon hall of the ancient dwarves. Right at
the mountains route. It is almost dark so that its vastness can only be dimly
guessed. But rising from the near side of the rocky floor there is a great
glow. The glow of smog. There he lay a vast red golden dragon fast asleep. A
thrming came from his jaws and nostrils, and wisps of smoke, but his fires were
low in slumber. Beneath him, under all his limbs and his huge coiled tail, and
about him, on all sides, stretching away across the unseen floors, lay countless
piles of precious things, gold rot, and unrot gems and jewels, and silver red
stained in the ruddy light. smou lay with wings folded like an immeasurable
bat turned partly on one side so that the hobbit could see his underparts and
his long pale belly crusted with gems and fragments of gold from his long
lying on his costly bed. Behind him, where the walls were nearest, could
dimly be seen coats of mail, helms and axes, swords and spears hanging, and
there in rows stood great jars and vessels filled with a wealth that could
not be guessed. To say that Bilbo's breath was taken away is no description
at all. There are no words left to express his staggerment, since men
changed the language that they learned of elves in the days when all the world
was wonderful. Bilbo had heard tell and sing of dragon hordes before, but the
splendor, the lust, the glory of such treasure had never yet come home to him.
His heart was filled and pierced with enchantment and with the desire of
dwarves, and he gazed motionless, almost forgetting the frightful guardian at the
gold beyond price and count. He gazed for what seemed an age before, drawn
almost against his will, he stole from the shadow of the doorway across the
floor to the nearest edge of the mounds of treasure.
Above him the sleeping dragon lay a dire menace even in his sleep. He grasped a
great two-handled cup as heavy as he could carry, and cast one fearful eye
upwards. Smow stirred a wing, opened a claw. The rumble of his snoring changed
its note. Then Bil fled, but the dragon did not wake not yet, but shifted into
other dreams of greed and violence, lying there in his stolen hall, while
the little hobbit toiled back up the long tunnel. His heart was beating in a
more fevered shaking was in his legs than when he was going down. But still
he clutched the cup, and his chief thought was, "I've done it. This will
show them more like a grosser than a burglar indeed. Well, we'll hear no more
of that. Nor did he. Balon was overjoyed to see the hobbit again, and as
delighted as he was surprised, he picked Bilbo up and carried him out into the
open air. It was midnight, and clouds had covered the stars, but Bilbo lay
with his eyes shut, gasping and taking pleasure in the feel of the fresh air
again. and hardly noticing the excitement of the dwarves, or how they
praised him and patted him on the back, and put themselves and all their
families for generations to come at his service. The dwarves were still passing
the cup from hand to hand, and talking delightedly of the recovery of their
treasure, when suddenly a vast rumbling woke in the mountain underneath, as if
it was an old volcano that had made up its mind to start eruptions once again.
The door behind them was pulled nearly too, and blocked from closing with a
stone. But up the long tunnel came the dreadful echoes from far down in the
depths of a bellowing and a trampling that made the ground beneath them
tremble. Then the dwarves forgot their joy in their confident boasts of a
moment before and cowered down in fright. Smout was still to be reckoned
with. It does not do to leave a live dragon out of your calculations if you
live near him. Dragons may not have much real use for all their wealth, but they
know it to an ounce as a rule, especially after long possession, and
Smau was no exception. He had passed from an uneasy dream, in which a warrior
altogether insignificant in size, but provided with a bitter sword and great
courage, figured most unpleasantly to a doze, and from a deuce to wide waking.
There was a breath of strange air in his cave.
Could there be a draft from that little hole? He had never felt quite happy
about it, though it was so small, and now he glared at it in suspicion, and
wondered why he had never blocked it up.
Of late he had half fancied he had caught the dim echoes of a knocking
sound from far above that came down through it to his layer. He stirred and
stretched forth his neck to sniff. Then he missed the cup. Thieves, fire,
murder. Such a thing had not happened since first he came to the mountain. His
rage passes description, the sort of rage that is only seen when rich folk
that have more than they can enjoy, suddenly lose something that they have
long had but have never before used or wanted. His fire belched forth, the hall
smoked. He shook the mountain roots. He thrust his head in vain at the little
hole, and then, coiling his length together, roaring like thunder
underground, he sped from his deep layer through its great door, out into the
huge passages of the mountain palace, and up towards the front gate. To hunt
the whole mountain till he had caught the thief, and had torn and trampled
him, was his one thought. He issued from the gate. The waters rose in fierce
whistling steam, and up he soared blazing into the air, and settled on the
mountaintop in a spout of green and scarlet flame. The dwarves heard the
awful rumor of his flight, and they crouched against the walls of the grassy
terrace, cringing under boulders, hoping somehow to escape the frightful eyes of
the hunting dragon. There they would have all been killed if it had not been
for Bilbo once again. Quick, quick, he gasped. The door, the tunnel.
It's no good here. Roused by these words, they were just about to creep
inside the tunnel when Bifur gave a cry.
My cousins, Bomb and Boler, we have forgotten them. They are down in the valley.
They will be slain and all our police too, and all our stores lost, moaned the
others. We can do nothing.
Nonsense, said Thoren, recovering his dignity. We cannot leave them. Get
inside Mr. Baggins and Balin, and you two, Fely and Killy the Dragon, shall
have all of us. Now, you others. Where are the ropes? Be quick. Those were
perhaps the worst moments they had been through yet. The horrible sounds of
Smau's anger were echoing in the stony hollows far above. At any moment he
might come blazing down or fly whirling round and find them there near the
perilous cliff's edge, hauling madly on the ropes. Up came Bofor, and still all
was safe. Up came Bombour, puffing and blowing while the ropes creaked, and
still all was safe. Up came some tools and bundles of stores, and then danger
was upon them. A worring noise was heard. A red light touched the points of
standing rocks. The dragon came. They had barely time to fly back to the
tunnel, pulling and dragging in their bundles, when Smau came hurling from the
north, licking the mountain sides with flame, beating his great wings with a
noise like a roaring wind. His hot breath shriveled the grass before the
door, and drove in through the crack they had left, and scorched them as they lay hid.
Flickering fires leaped up, and black rock shadows danced. Then darkness fell
as he passed again. The ponies screamed with terror, burst their robes, and
galloped wildly off. The dragon swooped and turned to pursue them, and was gone.
"That'll be the end of our poor beasts," said Thoren. "Nothing can escape Smog
once he sees it. Here we are, and here we shall have to stay, unless anyone
fancies trapping the long open miles back to the river with Smog on the watch."
It was not a pleasant thought. They crept further down the tunnel, and there
they lay and shivered, though it was warm and stuffy, until dawn came pale
through the crack of the door. Every now and again through the night they could
hear the roar of the flying dragon grow, and then pass and fade, as he hunted
round and round the mountain sides.
He guessed from the ponies, and from the traces of the camps he had discovered,
that men had come up from the river and the lake, and had skilled the
mountainside from the valley where the ponies had been standing. But the door
withtood his searching eye, and the little highwalled bay had kept out his
fiercest flames. Long he had hunted in vain till the dawn chilled his wrath,
and he went back to his golden couch to sleep, and to gather new strength. He
would not forget or forgive the theft, not if a thousand years turned him to
smoldering stone, but he could afford to wait. Slow and silent, he crept back to
his layer, and half closed his eyes.
When morning came, the terror of the dwarves grew less. They realized that
dangers of this kind were inevitable in dealing with such a guardian, and that
it was no good giving up their quest yet. Nor could they get away just now,
as Thoren had pointed out. Their ponies were lost or killed, and they would have
to wait some time before Smugg relaxed his watch sufficiently for them to dare
the long way on foot. Luckily, they had saved enough of their stores to last
them still for some time. They debated long on what was to be done, but they
could think of no way of getting rid of Smog, which had always been a weak point
in their plans, as Bilbo felt inclined to point out. Then, as is the nature of
folk that are thoroughly perplexed, they began to grumble at the Hobbit, blaming
him for what had at first so pleased them for bringing away a cup and
stirring up Smouth's wrath so soon.
"What else do you suppose a burglar is to do?" asked Bilbo angrily. I was not
engaged to kill dragons, that is warriors work, but to steal treasure. I
made the best beginning I could. Did you expect me to trot back with the whole
horde of thrower on my back? If there is any grumbling to be done, I think I
might have a say. You ought to have brought 500 burglars, not one. I am sure
it reflects great credit on your grandfather, but you cannot pretend that
you ever made the vast extent of his wealth clear to me. I should want
hundreds of years to bring it all up if
I was 50 times as big and smugg as tame as a rabbit. After that, of course, the
drawers begged his pardon. "What then do you propose we should do, Mr. Baggins?"
asked Thoren politely. "I have no idea at the moment. If you mean about
removing the treasure, that obviously depends entirely on some new turn of
luck in the getting rid of smog. Getting rid of dragons is not at all in my line,
but I will do my best to think about it.
Personally, I have no hopes at all and wish I was safe back at home. Never mind
that for the moment. What are we to do now today?
Well, if you really want my advice, I should say we can do nothing but stay
where we are. By day, we can no doubt creep out safely enough to take the air.
Perhaps before long, one or two could be chosen to go back to the store by the
river and replenish our supplies. But in the meanwhile, everyone ought to be well
inside the tunnel by night. Now, I will make you an offer. I have got my ring
and will creep down this very noon then if ever Smog ought to be napping and see
what he is up to. Perhaps something will turn up. Every worm has his weak spot,
as my father used to say, though I am sure it was not from personal experience.
Naturally, the dwarves accepted the offer eagerly. Already they had come to
respect little Bilbo. Now he had become the real leader in their adventure. He
had begun to have ideas and plans of his own. When midday came, he got ready for
another journey down into the mountain.
He did not like it, of course, but it
was not so bad now, he knew more or less
what was in front of him. Had he known more about dragons and their wy ways, he
might have been more frightened and less hopeful of catching this one napping.
The sun was shining when he started, but it was as dark as night in the tunnel.
The light from the door almost closed, soon faded as he went down. So silent
was his going that smoke on a gentle wind could hardly have surpassed it, and
he was inclined to feel a bit proud of himself as he drew near the lower door.
There was only the very faintest glow to be seen. Old Smog is weary and asleep,
he thought. He can't see me, and he won't hear me. Cheer up, Bilbo. He had
forgotten or had never heard about dragon's sense of smell. It is also an
awkward fact that they can keep half an eye open watching while they sleep if
they are suspicious.
Smog certainly looked fast asleep, almost dead and dark, with scarcely a
snore more than a width of unseen steam, when Bilbo peeped once more from the
entrance. He was just about to step out onto the floor when he caught a sudden
thin and piercing ray of red from under the drooping lid of Smau's left eye. He
was only pretending to sleep. He was watching the tunnel entrance. Hurriedly,
Bilbo stepped back and blasted the luck of his ring. Then Smoke,
"Well, thief, I smell you and I feel your air. I hear your breath. Come
along. Help yourself again. There is plenty and to spare.
But Bilbo was not quite so unlearned in dragon lore as all that. And if Smald
hoped to get him to come nearer so easily, he was disappointed. No thank
you, Om the tremendous, he replied. I did not come for presents. I only wish
to have a look at you and see if you were truly as great as Tails say.
I did not believe them. Do you now? said the dragon somewhat flattered, even
though he did not believe a word of it.
Truly songs and tales fall utterly short of the reality. Oh smug, the chiefest
and greatest of calamities, replied Bobo. You have nice manners for a thief
and a liar, said the dragon. You seem familiar with my name, but I don't seem
to remember smelling you before. Who are you, and where do you come from? Me, I
ask. You may indeed. I come from under the hill and under the hills and over
the hills my paths led and through the air I am he that walks unseen.
So I can well believe said Smal but that is hardly your usual name. I am the
cluefinder, the web cutter, the stinging fly. I was chosen for the lucky number.
Lovely titles, sneered the dragon. But lucky numbers don't always come off. I
am he that buries his friends alive and drowns them and draws them alive again
from the water. I came from the end of a bag, but no bag went over me. These
don't sound so credable, scoffed Smog. I am the friend of bears and the guest of
eagles. I am ringing winner and luckwearer, and I am barrel rider. When
on Bilbo, beginning to be pleased with his riddling.
That's better, said Smal. But don't let your imagination run away with you.
This, of course, is the way to talk to dragons if you don't want to reveal your
proper name, which is wise, and don't want to infuriate them by a flat
refusal, which is also very wise. No dragon can resist the fascination of
riddling talk and of wasting time trying to understand it. There was a lot here
which Smau did not understand at all, though I expect you do, since you know
all about Bilbo's adventures, to which he was referring, but he thought he
understood enough, and he chuckled in his wicked inside.
I thought so last night, he smiled to himself. Lakemen, some nasty scheme of
those miserable tub trading lakemen, or I'm a lizard. I haven't been down that
way for an age and an age, but I will soon alter that. Very well, O Barrerow
Rider, he said aloud. Maybe Barl was your pony's name, and maybe not, though
it was fat enough. You may walk unseen, but you did not walk all the way. Let me
tell you, I ate six ponies last night, and I shall catch and eat all the others
before long. In return for the excellent meal, I will give you one piece of
advice for your good. Don't have more to do with dwarves than you can help.
Dwarves, said Bilbo in pretended surprise. Don't talk to me, said Smal. I
know the smell and taste of dwarf no one better. Don't tell me that I can eat a
dwarf ridden pony and not know it.
You'll come to a bad end if you go with such friends. Thief barrel rider. I
don't mind if you go back and tell them so for me. But he did not tell Bilbo
that there was one smell he could not make out at all. Hobbit smell. It was
quite outside his experience and puzzled him mightily.
I suppose you got a fair price for that cup last night, he went on. Come now,
did you? Nothing at all. Well, that's just like them. and I suppose they are
sking outside and your job is to do all the dangerous work and get what you can
when I'm not looking for them and you will get a fair share. Don't you believe
it? If you get off alive, you will be lucky." Bilbo was now beginning to feel
really uncomfortable. Whenever Smoud's roving eye, seeking for him in the
shadows, flashed across him, he trembled, and an unaccountable desire
seized hold of him to rush out and reveal himself and tell all the truth to
Smal. In fact, he was in grievous danger of coming under the dragon spell. But
plucking up courage, he spoke again.
"You don't know everything, O Smog the mighty," said he. "Not gold alone
brought us hither." Ha ha. You admit the s laughed smug. Why not say us 14 and be
done with it, Mr. Lucky number? I am pleased to hear that you had other
business in these parts besides my gold.
In that case, you may perhaps not altogether waste your time. I don't know
if it is occurred to you that even if you could steal the gold bit by bit a
matter of a hundred years or so, you could not get it very far. Not much use
on the mountain side. Not much use in the forest. Bless me. Had you never
thought of the catch? A 14th share, I suppose, or something like it. Those were the terms. E.
But what about delivery?
What about cardage? What about armed guards and tolls? And Smog laughed
aloud. He had a wicked and a wily heart, and he knew his guesses were not far
out, though he suspected that the lakemen were at the back of the plants,
and that most of the plunder was meant to stop there in the town by the shore
that in his young days had been called Esgaroth.
You will hardly believe it, but poor Bilbo was really very takenback.
So far, all his thoughts and energies had been concentrated on getting to the
mountain and finding the entrance. He had never bothered to wonder how the
treasure was to be removed. Certainly never how any part of it that might fall
to his share was to be brought back all the way to Bag and Underh Hill. Now a
nasty suspicion began to grow in his mind. Had the dwarves forgotten this
important point, too, or were they laughing in their sleeves at him all the
time? That is the effect that dragon talk has on the inexperienced.
Bilbo, of course, ought to have been on his guard, but Smow had rather an
overwhelming personality.
I tell you, he said, in an effort to remain loyal to his friends, and to keep
his end up, that gold was only an afterthought with us. We came over hill
and underhill by wave and wind for revenge. Surely, Osm the unassessibly
wealthy, you must realize that your success has made you some bitter enemies.
Then Smau really did laugh a devastating sound which shook Bilbo to the floor.
While far up in the tunnel the dwarves huddled together and imagined that the
Hobbit had come to a sudden and a nasty end. Revenge, he snorted, and the light
of his eyes lit the hall from floor to ceiling like scarlet lightning. Revenge.
The king under the mountain is dead. And where are his kin that dare seek revenge?
Jireian, Lord of Dale, is dead, and I have eaten his people like a wolf among
sheep. And where are his sons sons that dare approach me? I kill where I wish,
and none dare resist. I laid low the warriors of old, and their like is not
in the world today. Then I was, but young and tender. Now I am old and
strong, strong, strong, thief in the shadows. He gloated. My armor is like
tenfold shields, my teeth or swords, my claws spears, the shock of my tail a
thunderbolt, my wings a hurricane, and my breath death. I have always
understood, said Bilbo in a frightened squeak. The dragons were softer
underneath, especially in the region of the chest, but doubtless one so
fortified his thought of that. The dragon stopped short in his boasting.
Your information is antiquated, he snapped. I am armored above and below
with iron scales and hard gems. No blade can pierce me. I might have guessed it,
said Bilbo. Truly, there can nowhere be found the equal of Lord Smau the
impenetrable. What magnificence to possess a waste coat of fine diamonds.
Yes, it is rare and wonderful indeed, said Smog, absurdly pleased. He did not
know that the hobbit had already caught a glimpse of his peculiar undercovering
on his previous visit and was itching for a closer view for reasons of his
own. The dragon rolled over. Knock, he said. What do you say to that?
Dazzlingly marvelous, perfect, flawless, staggering, exclaimed Bilbo aloud. But
what he thought inside was old fool.
why, there is a large patch in the hollow of his left breast as bare as a
snail out of its shell. After he had seen that Mr. Baggin's one idea was to get away.
Well, I really must not detain your magnificence any longer, he said, or
keep you from much needed rest. Ponies take some catching, I believe, after a
long start. and so do burglars," he added as a parting shot as he dotted
back and fled up the tunnel. It was an unfortunate remark, for the dragon
spouted terrific flames after him, and fast, though he sped up the slope, he
had not gone nearly far enough to be comfortable before the ghastly head of
Smugg was thrust against the opening behind. Luckily, the whole head and jaws
could not squeeze in, but the nostrils sent forth fire and vapor to pursue him,
and he was nearly overcome, and stumbled blindly on in great pain and fear. He
had been feeling rather pleased with the cleverness of his conversation with
Smog, but his mistake at the end shook him into better sense. "Never laugh at
live dragons, Bilbo, you fool," he said to himself, and it became a favorite
saying of his later, and passed into a proverb. You aren't nearly through this
adventure yet," he added. And that was pretty true as well. The afternoon was
turning into evening when he came out again and stumbled and fell in a faint
on the doorstep. The dwarfs revived him and doctorred his scorches as well as
they could. But it was a long time before the hair on the back of his head
and his heels grew properly again. It had all been singed and frizled right
down to the skin. In the meanwhile, his friends did their best to cheer him up,
and they were eager for his story, especially wanting to know why the
dragon had made such an awful noise, and how Bilbo had escaped. But the hobbit
was worried and uncomfortable, and they had difficulty in getting anything out
of him. On thinking things over, he was now regretting some of the things he had
said to the dragon, and was not eager to repeat them. The old Drush was sitting
on a rock nearby, with his head cocked on one side, listening to all that was
said. "It shows what an ill-temper Bilbo was in. He picked up a stone and threw
it at the thrush, which merely flooded aside and came back." "Drat the bird,"
said Bilbo crossly. "I believe he is listening, and I don't like the look of
him." "Leave him alone," said Torin.
"The thrushes are good and friendly.
This is a very old bird indeed, and is maybe the last left of the ancient breed
that used to live about here, tamed to the hands of my father and grandfather.
They were a long lived and magical race, and this might even be one of those that
were alive then, a couple of hundreds of years or more ago. The men of Dale used
to have the trick of understanding their language, and use them for messengers to
fly to the men of the lake and elsewhere. Well, he'll have news to take
to Lake Town. All right, if that is what he is after, said Bilbo, though I don't
suppose there are any people left there that trouble with thrush language.
Why, what has happened? cried the dwarves. Do get on with your tale. So
Bilbo told them all he could remember, and he confessed that he had a nasty
feeling that the dragon guessed too much from his riddles, added to the camps and
the ponies. I am sure he knows we came from Lake Town and had help from there,
and I have a horrible feeling that his next move may be in that direction. I
wish to goodness I had never said that about Barl Rider. It would make even a
blind rabbit in these parts think of the lakemen. Well, well, it cannot be
helped, and it is difficult not to slip in talking to a dragon, or so I have
always heard, said Balon, anxious to comfort him. I think he did very well,
if you ask me. You found out one very useful thing at any rate, and got home
alive, and that is more than most can say who have had words with the likes of
Smau. It may be a mercy and a blessing
yet to know of the bare patch in the old worm's diamond waste coat. That turned
the conversation, and they all began discussing Dragons Lanes, historical,
dubious, and mythical, and the various sorts of stabs and jabs and undercuts,
and the different arts devices and strategys by which they had been
accomplished. The general opinion was that catching a dragon napping was not
as easy as it sounded, and the attempt to stick one or prod one asleep was more
likely to end in disaster than a bold frontal attack. All the while they
talked, the thrush listened, till at last, when the stars began to peep
forth, it silently spread its wings and flew away. And all the while they
talked, and the shadows lengthened, Bilbo became more and more unhappy, and
his forboding grew. At last he interrupted them. "I am sure we are very
unsafe here," he said, "and I don't see the point of sitting here. The dragon
has withered all the pleasant green, and anyway the night has come, and it is
cold, but I feel it in my bones that this place will be attacked again. Smoud
knows now how I came down to his hole, and you can trust him to guess where the
other end of the tunnel is. He will break all this side of the mountain to
bits, if necessary, to stop up our entrance, and if we are smashed with it,
the better he will like it. You are very gloomy, Mr. Baggins said Thorin. Why has
not Smile blocked the lower end then if he is so eager to keep us out? He has
not or we should have heard him. I don't know. I don't know. Because at first he
wanted to try and lure me in again, I suppose, and now perhaps because he is
waiting till after tonight's hunt, or because he does not want to damage his
bedroom if he can help it. But I wish you would not argue. Smuggle will be
coming out at any minute now, and our only hope is to get well in the tunnel
and shut the door. He seemed so much in earnest that the dwarves at last did as
he said, though they delayed shutting the door. It seemed a desperate plan,
for no one knew whether or how they could get it open again from the inside,
and the thought of being shut in a place from which the only way out led through
the dragon's layer was not one they liked. Also, everything seemed quite
quiet. both outside and down the tunnel.
So for a longish while they sat inside, not far down from the halfopen door, and
went on talking. The talk turned to the dragon's wicked words about the dwarves.
Bilder wished he had never heard them, or at least that he could feel quite
certain that the dwarves now were absolutely honest when they declared
that they had never thought at all about what would happen after the treasure had
been won. We knew it would be a desperate venture, said Thorin, and we
know that still, and I still think that when we have won, it will be time enough
to think what to do about it. As for your share, Mr. Baggins, I assure you,
we are more than grateful, and you shall choose your own 14th as soon as we have
anything to divide. I am sorry if you are worried about transport, and I admit
the difficulties are great. The lands have not become less wild with the
passing of time, rather the reverse. But we will do whatever we can for you and
take our share of the cost when the time comes. Believe me or not, as you like.
From that the talk turned to the great horde itself, and to the things that
Thoren and Balin remembered. They wondered if they were still lying there
unharmed in the hole below. The spears that were made for the armies of the
great King Bladderan, long since dead, each had a thrice forged head and their
shafts were inlaid with cunning gold, but they were never delivered or paid
for. Shields made for warriors long dead. The great golden cup of Thor,
two-handed, hammered and cared with birds and flowers, whose eyes and petals
were of jewels, coats of male, gilded and silvered and impenetrable.
The necklace of Jiren, Lord of Dale, made of 500 emeralds, green as grass,
which he gave for the arming of his eldest son in the coat of dwarfl rings,
the like of which had never been made before, for it was rot of pure silver to
the power and strength of triple steel.
But fairest of all was the great white gem which the dwarves had found beneath
the roots of the mountain. The heart of the mountain, the ark and stone of Thrain.
The ark and stone. The ark and stone, murmured Thoren in the dark, half
dreaming with his chin upon his knees.
It was like a globe with a thousand facets. It shone like silver in the fire
light, like water in the sun, like snow under the stars, like rain upon the moon.
But the enchanted desire of the horde had fallen from Bilbo. All through their
talk he was only half listening to them.
He sat nearest to the door with one ear cocked for any beginnings of a sound
without. His other was alert for echoes beyond the murmurss of the dwarves, for
any whisper of a movement from far below. Darkness grew deeper, and he grew
ever more uneasy. "Shut the door," he begged them. "I fear that dragon in my
marrow. I like this silence far less than the uproar of last night. Shut the
door before it is too late. Something in his voice gave the dwars an
uncomfortable feeling. Slowly Thoren shook off his dreams, and getting up, he
kicked away the stone that wedged the door. Then they thrust upon it, and it
closed with a snap and a clang. No trace of a keyhole was there left on the
inside. They were shut in the mountain, and not a moment too soon. They had
hardly gone any distance down the tunnel when a blow smoked the side of the
mountain like the crash of battering rams made of forest oaks and swung by
giants. The rock boomed, the walls cracked, and stones fell from the roof on their heads.
What would have happened if the door had still been open?
I don't like to think. They fled further down the tunnel, glad to be still alive,
while behind them outside they heard the roar and rumble of Smog's fury. He was
breaking rocks to pieces, smashing wall and cliff with the lashings of his huge
tail to their little lofty camping ground, the scorched grass, the thrush's
stone, the snail covered walls, the narrow ledge, and all disappeared in a
jumble of smitherines, and an avalanche of splintered stones fell over the cliff
into the valley below.
Smile had left his lair in silent stealth, quietly soared into the air,
and then floated heavy and slow in the dark like a monstrous crow down the wind
towards the west of the mountain, in the hopes of catching unawares something or
somebody there, and of spying the outlet to the passage which the thief had used.
This was the outburst of his wrath, when he could find nobody, and see nothing,
even where he guessed the outlet must actually be. After he had let off his
rage in this way, he felt better, and he thought in his heart that he would not
be troubled again from that direction.
In the meanwhile, he had further vengeance to take. "Barrel rider," he
snorted. "Your feet came from the wateride, and up the water you came
without a doubt. I don't know your smell, but if you are not one of those
men of the lake, you had their help.
They shall see me and remember who was the real king under the mountain."
He rose in fire and went away south towards the running river. Chapter 13.